A Guide to the Papers of Michael J. Stolee, 1964 to 2009
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of Michael J. Stolee 1964 to 2009
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
102;
21 Hollinger document cases, 1 half document case, 1 oversize box, and 1 multimedia box.
Contains material related to Stolee’s work as an expert witness in 68 school desegregation cases in the US including Norfolk. Stolle helped to design Norfolk 1971 school busing plan.The material includes the court proceedings, testimony, newspaper clippings, photographs, invoices and correspondence as well as his narrative of some of the cases.
Micheal J. Stolee
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
A gift from Marilyn Stolee on October 3, 2008.
Biographical Information
Dr. Michael J. Stolee was a Norwegian Lutheran native of the Minneapolis-St. Paul area in Minnesota, born on August 22, 1930. He attended the city's public schools - Jenny Lind Elementary School and Henry Junior-Senior High School. Later, he enrolled at St. Olaf College where he earned his bachelor's degree with teaching majors in history and speech. Stolee first taught history and speech in rural Minnesota public schools before enrolling in graduate study at the University of Minnesota in late 1952. There he completed his master's degree and his doctorate in Educational Administration with an emphasis on school leadership in the legal context. Stolee completed his Ph.D. in 1963. Following his administrative experience in Minnesota schools, Stolee served as a faculty member at the University of Miami, the University of Massachusetts-Amherst, and the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, teaching the legal aspects of school administration. At the latter, he served as Dean of the School of Education for nine years. In addition to his regular faculty appointments, Dr. Stolee was a visiting professor at Appalachian State University and was an external examiner for the faculties of education at the University of Guyana and the University of the West Indies. At the University of Miami, he was co-director of an institute on desegregation for school board members and superintendents in Florida and South Georgia. This was the first institute funded under the Civil Rights Act of 1964.
Dr. Stolee's education and personal experience prepared him to address the issues created by the Brown v. Board of Education decision of 1954. Stolee cited his experience with black students at the University of Minnesota during graduate school as one of the first that indicated to him the future need for addressing racial cooperation in the education world. His first experience with overt racial segregation came during his spring break in 1963 when he and his wife stopped at a Dairy Queen near Ocala, Florida. The sign in the window said "White Only." They thought it had to do with the availability of only vanilla ice cream.
In 1965, Dr. Stolee and a colleague, Dr. Robert Wey of the University Of Miami School Of Education, suggested that a consultation center be established at Miami for the purpose of helping to put the law into practice regarding Brown v. Board. The Florida School Desegregation Consulting Center at the University of Miami was subsequently born and ran from July 1, 1965 until 1981. The center served as an advisory entity to school systems across the nation. While acting as Director of the Center and later after he had been promoted as Dean of Education at Miami, Dr. Stolee participated in the desegregation proceedings of many school systems across the United States. The city of Norfolk, Virginia is one of over 350 school jurisdictions where Dr. Stolee advised on school desegregation methods and busing plans.
Dr. Stolee had an impact on the Hampton Roads area as an expert witness on the 1971 Norfolk Public Schools busing desegregation plan. Stolee testified on several occasions between May 7, 1969 and April 1971. During his initial court depositions, he stated that Norfolk Public Schools should discontinue its 'freedom of choice' policy of pupil assignment that allowed schools to remain segregated. Dr. Stolee presented findings indicating that there would be no educational decline for black or white students, should they be bussed together to larger, integrated schools. After his earlier testimony, Stolee presented a plan to U.S. District Judge Walter Hoffman in May of 1969 proposing to do away with the 'freedom of choice' system for Norfolk students and increasing desegregation by busing. Stolee's proposed feeder system for Norfolk assigned schools to groups (two white schools, one black school) so that elementary schools had a well-integrated student population. There was a prolonged court battle to get Norfolk Public Schools to adopt the Stolee plan, but by April of 1971, a U.S. Supreme Court ruling was in place ordering the schools to use Dr. Stolee's plan in the creation of a desegregated school system.
Following his career at Miami, Stolee returned to his native Wisconsin and joined the faculty at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, while continuing his school system desegregation planning as a consultant. Between 1981 and 1995, Stolee and several educational scholar colleagues were involved in developing busing and schooling plans to smoothly integrate Benton Harbor Area Schools with nearby Coloma Community Schools and Eau Claire Public Schools in southwestern Michigan. The Benton Harbor situation began with a 1981 court ruling that ordered the community to work with neighboring school districts to integrate schools and provide busing solutions for the Benton Harbor, Coloma, and Eau Claire areas. Dr. Michael J. Stolee was appointed Special Master as part of a case remedy by Judge Douglass W. Hillman, of the U. S. District Courts of Michigan. Stolee's job in this role was to serve as an advisor and liaison between the Court and the Benton Harbor communities involved in the case and its remedial processes.
Dr. Michael J. Stolee passed away in March 29, 2007 at the age of 76.
Scope and Content
The collection documents Stolee's work as a court and school system-appointed advisor in school desegregation cases in 68 school districts. The most extensively documented work is the protracted legal battle centering on Benton Harbor, Michigan, and efforts to integrate its school systems. The collection also includes biographical material on Stolee, historical material on school desegregation and material about the establishment and operation of the Florida Desegregation Center at the University of Miami.
Other professionals documented in this collection are Dr. Janice Sodos, a Milwaukee superintendent and consultant and Herbert Norder.
Dr. Stolee's papers range in date from 1964 to 2009, with the bulk being from the late 1970s to 1999. Materials in the collection include newspaper clippings, lecture transparencies, court orders and depositions, work schedules, school desegregation plans, Congressional records, term papers, notepads, maps, photographs, drawings, handwritten notes, brochures, computer disks, bound notebooks, speeches and a memoir.
Contents List
- Historical and Biographical information
  This series is broken into six sub-series.
  - Dr. Michael J. Stolee Biographical Materials 1968 to 2009
    This sub-series contains biographical information about Stolee’s career. Some of these materials were compiled for the purpose of writing his memoir describing his motivation for involvement in education, as well as reflections on his career. Included are personal recollections of his experiences with desegregation; correspondence; Dr. Stolee’s curriculum vita; case histories; awards; appointments and resignations; letters of appreciation and recommendation; Stolee’s memoir drafts; and a compilation of biographical materials put together by Dr. Stolee’s wife, Marilyn.
    alphabetical
    - Appointments and Resignations 1972-83 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Biographical Materials Compiled by Marilyn Stolee 2009 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Correspondence May 2003 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Curriculum Vita: Michael J. Stolee undated (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Distinguished Alumni Award, St. Olaf College 1972 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Letters of Appreciation to Dr. Michael J. Stolee 1968, 1989 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Letters of Recommendation for Dr. Michael J. Stolee 1978-79, 1999 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Lexis-Nexis printout of Dr. Stolee cases 1969-1987 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Memoirs – Drafts undated (Box-folder 1:9)
    - 10: Memoirs -- Research undated (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Tennessee Attorney Biographical Materials 2003
    This sub-series contains biographical materials for attorney’s involved in the Tennessee case, specifically Richard H. Dinkins and Avon Nyanza Williams, Jr.
    - Dinkins, Richard H. 2003 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Williams, Jr. Avon Nyanza 2003 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Historical Accounts September 5, 2005
    This sub-series contains Dr. Stolee’s historical accounts of desegregation cases in California, Michigan, and Virginia.
    - California - San Francisco Historical Account by Stolee September 5, 2005 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Michigan - Detroit Historical Account by Stolee September 5, 2005 (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Virginia - Roanoke Historical Account September 5, 2005 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Lectures 1967 to 1992
    This sub-series contains lecture materials related to school desegregation.
    - History of Desegregation: Janice Sodos’ Lecture to Future Principals April 20, 1988 (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Lecture transparencies 1968-1992 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Race Relations and the Schools in the United States: Decisions Leading To and Following Brown by Michael J. Stolee November 10, 1967 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - News Clippings 1966 to 1999
    This sub-series contains news clippings on topics related to desegregation, busing, and magnet schools.
    - Busing 1971, 1982 (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Desegregation 1966-1999 (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Gordon Foster 1994 (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Magnet Schools undated (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Other Published Materials 1976, 1992-1995
    This sub-series contains abstracts, book reviews, and other published materials related to school desegregation and some of the cases Dr. Stolee worked on.
    - Abstract: The Norfolk Decision: The Effects of Converting from a Unitary Educational System to a Dual Educational System upon Academic Achievement, by Vivian W. Ikpa 1992 (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Book Review: “Seeds of Crisis: Public Schooling in Milwaukee since 1920” 1995 (Box-folder 1:24)
    - “Desegregation in the Cities – Trends in School Segregation in the 1970s,” Congressional Record May-June 1976 (Box-folder 1:25)
- Miami School Desegregation Center 1964 to 1976
  This series documents the establishment of the University of Miami School of Education Florida School Desegregation Center. Included are correspondence, reports, budgets, proposals, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photos, and conference information.
  chronological
  - Correspondence 1964-69 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Florida and South Georgia Institute for Superintendents and Board Members on the Civil Rights Act of 1964 February 24-26, 1965 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Proposal for Establishing a Consultative Center for the Solving of Problems Caused by School Desegregation 1965 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Memo Reports of Center Activities 1966 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Newsletter – The Consultant South Florida School Desegregation Consulting Center 1966-67 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - “School Management – How to Play the Game,” February 16-17, 1967 (Box-folder 1:31)
  - News Clippings 1967-1974 (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Proposed Budgets for South Florida School Desegregation Consulting Center 1967-69 (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Florida Governor’s Commission on Urban Development 1968 (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Inquiry: The Quarterly Magazine of the University of Miami, Winter 1968 (Box-folder 1:35)
  - University of Miami Conference March 26, 1971 (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Miscellaneous 1972-76 (Box-folder 1:37)
  - Photos undated (Box-folder 1:38)
- School Desegregation Cases
  This series includes court documents, correspondence, invoices, minutes, photographs, notes and newspaper clippings from school desegregation cases in twenty-five states. The largest bulk of material is related to the Michigan court case Barbara Jean Berry, et al., Plaintiffs vs. School District of the City of Benton Harbor, et al., Defendant. In this case, Stolee served as Special Master for nearly two decades beginning with his appointment to this position in 1981. This case centered on desegregation and busing efforts in the Benton Harbor, Coloma, and Eau Claire school districts.
  - Alabama 1983 to 1995
    This sub-series includes Mobile from 1983-1990 and Tuscaloosa from 1993 to 1995.
    - Mobile Plan June 25, 1986 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Mobile Desegregation 1983, 1989-90 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Tuscaloosa Fees and Expenses 1993-95 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Arkansas 1987 to 1989
    This sub-series includes Little Rock from 1987 to 1989.
    alphabatical
    - Little Rock Fees and Expenses 1987-89 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Little Rock Neighborhood / Cohort Plan undated (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Little Rock News Clippings 1987 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - California 1977 to 1982
    This sub-series includes Los Angeles from 1977 to 1982.
    - Los Angeles Desegregation 1977-82 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Colorado 1973 to 1985
    This sub-series includes Denver from 1973 to 1985.
    - Denver 1973-74, 1982-85 (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Denver News Clippings 1974, 1984 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Florida 1967 to 1996
    This sub-series includes Collier County from 1968-1971; Dade County from 1967-1975; Palm Beach County from 1988-89; Polk County from 1987 to 1993; St. Petersburg from 1992 and 1996; Tampa from 1995 to 1996; and Volusia County in 1970.
    - Collier County 1968-71 (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Dade County 1969-70 (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Dade County News Clippings 1967-75 (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Palm Beach County 1988-89 (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Polk County 1987-93 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - St. Petersburg 1992, 1996 (Box-folder 2:15)
    - St. Petersburg News Clippings 1996 (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Tampa 1995-96 (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Volusia County 1970 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Georgia 1972 to 1999
    This sub-series includes Atlanta from 1972-1973; DeKalb County from 1983-1984; and Savannah from 1986 to 1999.
    - Atlanta – Calhoun vs. Cook 1972-73 (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Atlanta News Clippings 1972-73 (Box-folder 2:20)
    - DeKalb County 1983-84 (Box-folder 2:21)
    - DeKalb County News Clippings 1984 (Box-folder 2:22)
    - Savannah 1986-91 (Box-folder 2:23)
    - Savannah Deposition April 20, 1988 (Box-folder 2:24)
    - Savannah – News Clippings 1980s-90s (Box-folder 2:25)
    - Savannah Plan 1986-88 (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Illinois 1976 to 1996
    This sub-series includes Chicago from 1994-1995; Champaign from 1980-1981; Rockford from 1990-1996; and Springfield from 1976 and 1988.
    - Chicago 1994-95 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Champaign 1980-81 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Champaign - News Clippings 1980-81 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Rockford 1992-96 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Rockford – Cross-examination undated (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Rockford – Fees and Expenses 1992-96 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Rockford – News Clippings 1993 (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Rockford Redirect Examination 1990 (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Rockford Transcript 1993 (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Springfield – Fees and Expenses 1988 (Box-folder 3:10)
    - Springfield – News clippings 1976 (Box-folder 3:11)
    - Springfield Transcript 1976 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Indiana 1981
    This sub-series includes Indianapolis in 1981.
    - Indianapolis – News Clippings 1981 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Kansas 1994
    This sub-series includes Topeka in 1994.
    - Topeka – “Topeka comes full circle,” MM Magazine April-May 1994 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Kentucky 1975 to 1999
    This sub-series includes Louisville from 1975; 1980; and 1998 to 1999.
    - Louisville Desegregation 1975, 1998-99 (Box-folder 3:15)
    - Louisville - News Clippings 1980, 1999 (Box-folder 3:16)
    - Louisville Transcript 1999 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Maryland 1972 to 1985
    This sub-series includes Prince George County from 1972; and 1984 to 1985.
    - Prince George’s County 1972 1984-85 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Massachusetts 1972 to 2005
    This sub-series includes Boston from 1972; 1975; 1987; 1998 to 1999; and 2005.
    - Boston 1972, 1998, 2005 (Box-folder 3:19)
    - Boston – News Clippings 1975, 1987, 1999 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Michigan 1974 to 1999.
    This sub-series includes Benton Harbor, Eau Claire, Coloma, and Detroit from 1974 to 1999.
    - Court Documents – United States Court of Appeals, 6th District 1974 to 1986
      Barbara Jean Berry, et al., Plaintiffs vs. School District of the City of Benton Harbor, et al., Defendants
      - 6th Circuit Order November 1, 1974 (Box-folder 4:1)
      - District Court Liability August 22, 1977 (Box-folder 4:2)
      - Additional Defendants Liable August 7, 1978 (Box-folder 4:3)
      - 6th Circuit Affirmed January 24, 1983 (Box-folder 4:4)
      - Layoff of Black Teachers Moot September 29, 1986 (Box-folder 4:5)
    - Court Documents – United States District Court for the Western District of Michigan Southern Division 1980 to 1999
      - Order -- Michigan Education Association Motion for Intervention July 11, 1980 (Box-folder 4:6)
      - Court Transcript, Part 1 January 7, 1981 (Box-folder 4:7)
      - Court Transcript, Part 2 January 7, 1981 (Box 4:8)
      - Decision and Remedial Order May 1, 1981 (Box-folder 4:9)
      - Order – Implementation of Remedy Plan May 1, 1981 (Box-folder 4:10)
      - Order -- Appointing Dr. Michael J. Stolee, as Special Master May 5, 1981 (Box-folder 4:11)
      - Supplemental Order -- Eamon Property Transfer May 20, 1981 (Box-folder 4:12)
      - Order – Appointing James P. Comer as Special Master June 3, 1981 (Box-folder 4:13)
      - Supplemental Order -- In-Service Training June 4, 1981 (Box-folder 4:14)
      - Fees and Expenses, Dr. Joseph H. McMillan June 30, 1981 (Box-folder 4:15)
      - Order -- McCord King Junior High School Remodel June 30, 1981 (Box-folder 4:16)
      - Supplemental Remedy Order -- Pupil Reassignment, Community Education Council, Teacher Transfers June 30, 1981 (Box-folder 4:17)
      - Order –Bus Purchase July 15, 1981 (Box-folder 4:18)
      - Order -- Magnet Approval August 12, 1981 (Box-folder 4:19)
      - Order -- Benton Harbor Buses August 18, 1981 (Box-folder 4:20)
      - Supplemental Order -- Comer Report September 3, 1981 (Box-folder 4:21)
      - Order -- Community Education Council Director, September 18, 1981 (Box-folder 4:22)
      - Order -- Coloma Student, Eddie J. Glaspy, October 22, 1981 (Box-folder 4:23)
      - Supplemental Order -- Students, Ballard October 23, 1981 (Box-folder 4:24)
      - Order -- Benton Harbor Transportation Director November 18, 1981 (Box-folder 4:25)
      - Order – Payment of Expenses, Lake Michigan College November 18, 1981 (Box-folder 4:26)
      - Order -- Social Achievement Model November 27, 1981 (Box-folder 4:27)
      - School Admission Order -- Student, Winbush March 10, 1982 (Box-folder 4:28)
      - Order -- Eau Claire Middle School April 23, 1982 (Box-folder 4:29)
      - Supplemental Order – Special Education Payments, Title I Payments, Special Master, Transportation, Achievement May 26, 1982 (Box-folder 4:30)
      - Ex Parte Temporary Order -- Summer Transportation June 21, 1982 (Box-folder 4:31)
      - Order -- Calendar August 31, 1982 (Box-folder 4:32)
      - Order – Coloma Layoffs October 1982 (Box-folder 4:33)
      - Supplemental Opinion and Order -- School Sales, Transportation Costs, Title I, Special Education, Magnet Programs October 28, 1982 (Box-folder 4:34)
      - Supplemental Transportation Order -- Transportation January 13, 1983 (Box-folder 4:35)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Herbert Norder April 28, 1983 (Box-folder 4:36)
      - Supplemental Opinion and Order – State of Michigan’s Motion to Vacate, May 13, 1983 (Box-folder 4:37)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Herbert Norder June 14, 1983 (Box-folder 4:38)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Wayne State University August 23, 1983 (Box-folder 4:39)
      - Order – Payment of Computer Expert Fees, Herbert Norder December 6, 1983 (Box-folder 4:40)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Wayne State University December 12, 1983 (Box-folder 4:41)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Herbert Norder January 19, 1984 (Box-folder 4:42)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Herbert Norder April 6, 1984 (Box-folder 4:43)
      - Order -- Magnet Money April 11, 1984 (Box-folder 4:44)
      - Order – Eau Claire Transport June 29, 1984 (Box-folder 4:45)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Wayne State University July 16, 1984 (Box-folder 4:46)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, R. Radio July 29, 1984 (Box-folder 4:47)
      - Order -- Comer Model – Money August 9, 1984 (Box-folder 4:48)
      - Supplemental Remedial Order -- Transportation Coordinator August 29, 1984 (Box-folder 4:49)
      - Order -- Attorney Fees November 20, 1984 (Box-folder 4:50)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, James P. Comer December 3, 1984 (Box-folder 4:51)
      - Order -- Attorney Fees January 11, 1985 (Box-folder 5:1)
      - Order -- Michigan Education Association / Coloma Layoffs January 21, 1985 (Box-folder 5:2)
      - Order – Regarding Chapter I Funds July 11, 1985 (Box-folder 5:3)
      - Order – Regarding Berrien County Intermediate School District Petition for Clarification August 9, 1985 (Box-folder 5:4)
      - Order -- Berrien County Intermediate School District Petition for Clarification Moot February 21, 1986 (Box-folder 5:5)
      - Order -- Morris Thompson Rehire Moot February 21, 1986 (Box-folder 5:6)
      - Opinion -- Granting Attorney Fees and Costs July 30, 1986 (Box-folder 5:7)
      - Order -- Calendar – Martin Luther King Day September 5, 1986 (Box-folder 5:8)
      - Order -- NAACP Motion for Admittance Granted November 12, 1986 (Box-folder 5:9)
      - Order -- Layoff of Black Teachers Moot November 19, 1986 (Box-folder 5:10)
      - Order -- Calendar December 13, 1986 (Box-folder 5:11)
      - Opinion -- Denying NAACP-SCF’s Petition for Reconsideration of Award of Attorney Fees February 9, 1987 (Box-folder 5:12)
      - Fees and Expenses, Dr. Michael J. Stolee January 1, 1986 – February 18, 1987 (Box-folder 5:13)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Dr. Michael J. Stolee October 13, 1987 (Box-folder 5:14)
      - Order -- Comer Model October 23, 1987 (Box-folder 5:15)
      - Fees and Expenses, Dr. Michael J. Stolee February 27, 1987 – March 20, 1988 (Box-folder 5:16)
      - Order – Appointing Janice I. Sodos as Court Expert May 6, 1988 (Box-folder 5:17)
      - Order – Regarding Berrien County Intermediate School District Transportation Coordinator May 6, 1988 (Box-folder 5:18)
      - Order – Regarding Berrien County Intermediate School District Telecommunications Program May 18, 1988 (Box-folder 5:19)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Janice I. Sodos November 17, 1988 (Box-folder 5:20)
      - Order – Fees and Expenses, Dr. Eddie J. Moore November 21, 1988 (Box-folder 5:21)
      - Stipulation and Order Substituting Counsel of Record December 1988 (Box-folder 5:22)
      - Order -- Berrien County Intermediate School District Vocational Tech January 22, 1989 (Box-folder 5:23)
      - Fees and Expenses, Dr. Michael J. Stolee March 21, 1988 – February 20, 1989 (Box-folder 5:24)
      - Order – Regarding Transfer of Chapter I Funds May 1, 1989 (Box-folder 5:25)